Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna and the
emptiness of the Medicine Buddha.
And we've reached the next chapter,
which is chapter 12.
Don't forget our goal is to finish 27
chapters
in 5 years, and this is the third year,
and we're making good progress. Uh we're
already to the 12th chapter.
And again, this is a pariksha, which
means what?
And investigation. And this time we're
going to investigate dukha.
Suffering.
Suffering, yay. Okay, so
I don't know about you, but you feel
like, "Oh, finally he got to the
subject, you know."
Uh I would like to investigate all the
mess in in my life. All the messes in my
life, I would like to investigate
and find out why they're happening,
okay? So, like, why did this COVID come?
You know, why is my partner grumpy
sometimes? And
why is my dog peeing in the house and
stuff? Big things like that, you know.
So, uh
this is the call uh da key che pa don
shin key che pa do pa,
which means an examination
of investigation
of
is the pain, the trouble in my life,
is it coming from me
or is it coming from something else,
okay? And And the me here
is da.
So, that can also mean
does the pain in my Does the trouble in
my life
come from the trouble in my life
or does it come from something else?
Does the trouble in my life
come from the itself or from something
else? Okay, I'll say it again.
Does Do the problems in my life
come from the problems in my life
or do they come from something else? And
then actually, Nagarjuna splits it
into two, okay?
Do the problems in my life
come from the problems in my life, or do
they come from something else? And
who gives me the problems in my life? Is
it me, or is it somebody else? Who gives
me trouble?
Is it always me giving myself trouble?
So, we're discussing
self
and other in two different contexts.
Does the pain cause itself,
or does something else cause the pain?
Do I cause myself pain? Do I pain
myself?
Or does someone else pain me?
Okay, so those are the questions that
we're going to explore
in chapter 12. Let's go to the first
verse, okay?
Uh Katic dunya daki che shengi che da
nyige che
gime pa ne chu one da
deni chower nyur nyur
Then the guardian then gives you four
options
about does pain
cause itself?
Okay, forget me or you, okay? That's not
what we're talking about in the first
part. We're talking about
does the trouble in my life cause the
trouble in my life,
or does something else than the trouble
in my life cause the trouble in my life,
okay?
And the guardian then starts out and he
says, "You know,
this question is discussed by four
different groups of people, okay?
There's four
philosophical schools in ancient India,
right? 2,000 years ago,
who have an opinion
on this question. Katic means
different people say different things,
okay? What?
First choice, some of them say
dunya daki che
you know, my
the trouble in my life comes from the
trouble in my life, okay? That's the
first opinion.
All right, from itself.
Now, second opinion, shen chi che.
What's that?
Yeah, cuz somebody else
something other than the trouble in my
life causes the trouble in my life.
That's the second opinion.
Third opinion, ni ke che.
It's both of you guys. Uh the suffering
the trouble in your life causes the
trouble in your life and there's things
that aren't the trouble in your life
that also bring you trouble in your life
at the same time.
Third choice,
ah gi me.
Yeah, neither one. Okay? Nothing causes
the trouble in your life. It just
happens.
Okay? Ne tso wa do.
De ni tso wa mi no lo. Yeah, you're all
wrong.
Wait a minute. One of them has to be
right. There's only four possibilities.
He says, "No."
And
I think this is a good place to learn
some Sanskrit. Okay? So, in different
parts
of these classes, we've been learning
different kinds of Sanskrit and there's
some Sanskrit right here,
which I thought it would be useful to
throw in in right away.
And that is
by my by itself,
by something else, by both, by neither.
Let's learn the Sanskrit for those four
possibilities. Then let's learn the
Sanskrit for trouble in your life
cuz that's how we spend our life. Okay?
All right. So, here's the Sanskrit.
Uh
the first one uh
swayam
krta. Okay? Swayam krta. Swayam means as
came from itself. Okay?
Krta means made. Okay? The trouble in
your life swayam krta
comes from itself. Okay? The trouble in
your life comes from itself, right?
In Tibetan, dag gi che, it comes from
itself. Okay? This swaya in Sanskrit has
pieces like su and aya.
and Su means yourself.
And Aya means makes it a noun, okay?
Self selfness.
And we see this Su in English when we
say suicide. Side side means to kill.
And Su means yourself.
Self comes from Sui
uh Su and solitary comes from Su, okay?
So, all of those words
come from this Swaya, okay?
Also, the Indo-European is Sway.
And that came into self and secret. So,
all of these words meaning
self.
Karta
Karta comes from a verb Kr
which means to do.
And that's the root of the word
karma.
Okay.
And Kr just in general means to do
something. English cognates are serial,
create,
and karma, okay? Serial, there's there's
a time in history when C changed to S
sound.
And originally it was Ka, so create
and then serial, okay?
All right. So, these all mean to make.
Uh now, the second option
is that things are Para Karta Para
Karta.
Uh then
the trouble in my life comes from
something other than the trouble in my
life.
Or the trouble in my life is caused by
someone else other than me, okay? Second
choice. Para just means somebody else,
okay? Other guys.
All right. Third choice. Dwabhyang
Karta.
Dwabhyang Dwabhyang
Karta. Okay. The trouble in my life
comes from both
me and other people
or by itself and from other things,
okay? Both.
Okay. Dwa Dwa means two. It's That
That's why
the number two has a W in it.
And
it's also the B the W is the B in
bicycle for example.
And the word divide, okay.
Uh or the fourth choice is ahetuka.
Ahetuka. Hetu means
cause
cause a
not
not, okay. Ka means made by, okay.
Yeah, not made by causes ahetuka, okay.
So the last possibility is that the
trouble in your life just comes through
at random. There's you know, it's not
brought about by you or by other people.
It doesn't come from itself, it doesn't
come from something else, okay.
I like this word dukkha. I mean I don't
like dukkha, but I like the word.
Dukkha, okay. Du
is stands for DUS. The the S changes to
H in this context.
And so duce means bad.
I don't know, did you call people
ducebag in your in your high school? I
didn't know.
I'm sorry. Okay, forget that. Uh
duce means uh
Duce means bad. Okay. And it came into
English as DYS. I think through the
Greek, right? Dysfunctional
or
disease, okay.
And then the kha means the open
hub of a wheel. And traditionally dukkha
is explained as meaning a squeaky wheel.
Uh you know, they say what? The
Squeaky
The squeaky wheel makes the most noise.
Squeaky wheel gets the grease.
Uh yeah.
Yeah. Anyway, troublesome people make
the most noise. Something like that.
Uh so dukkha is traditionally explained
as being a bad a bad connection on your
wheel on your cart.
And then it goes on
Okay.
Kha is also found in Indo-European as
guy guy.
And that means
guy.
It means that to yawn or to gape with
your mouth, okay? And so, dukkha
basically is just a big mouth. Big bad
mouth, okay? And it means trouble.
Where does the dukkha
where does the trouble mind that come
from?
Is it uh svayam kritam?
Svayam krita, does it come from me
somehow?
Parakrita, does it come from somebody
else somehow?
Dvayam dvabhyam krita,
does it come from me and other people?
Or is it ahituka?
Or does it just happen? Things happen.
All right, that's the chapter that we're
going to be looking at. Let's go to the
next verse.
Okay.
Kalti dagyur chigyu naded chiteni
gyuming gyur kanchipam bodina nadeni
bodinang gyu.
Uh
When we're discussing the possibility
that pain has come from pain itself,
the gardener says, "What I mean is
did the mortal falling apart
body that you have and mind that you
have now,
did that come from a mortal falling
apart body and mind in the past life?"
Okay, that's what it means when he says
suffering causes suffering itself, okay?
Is it the nature of your body and mind
to suffer?
And
let's look at the possibility
that your body and mind, which are
falling apart,
and you can't stop it normally,
uh and it's funny the things that people
do to try to stop it.
I think half the things we try to do to
stop the suffering, the falling apart of
our body and mind, they just accelerate
the falling apart of our body and mind.
Anyway,
uh
Kelti,
he says here, okay. So, so the guardian
is says, "When I talk about pain coming
from pain, what I'm really talking about
is
what caused your body and mind right now
that's falling apart.
And let's look at the first possibility
that it's coming from the same thing in
the past. You had a body and mind that
was falling apart and then it created a
body and mind that's falling apart.
Okay, so here we go.
Kelti Daki Chig Yerno, if the body if
the problems you have in your life
are coming from the problems in your
life,
Dechir Tendey Jummyo, then we can say
that it did not come about by depending
on something else. Okay? If the trouble
in your life
has been caused by the trouble in your
life,
then we can say there's no dependence
there. It's not like the trouble in your
life has to depend on trouble in your
life cuz it's already trouble in your
life, okay?
Uh Pumba Kanchu Pumba Dida Latende Pumba
Dida Jo,
uh actually, uh
I should say
that even when you say suffering, Naku
Nagaru Nagaru is correcting the guy. I
would say though
that if you have a body and mind that's
falling apart,
it's a sign that you had a body and mind
that was falling apart
Okay, so maybe last life you had a body
and mind that was falling apart, you did
things,
you did uh not so nice things cuz your
body and mind was falling apart. And
then now in this life your body and
mind's falling apart, okay? So, falling
apart causes falling apart.
That's okay.
Uh
And then he by the way he says, uh
in that case,
uh if pain causes pain,
then
could you have come from your death? And
he says, "No." Okay? It's not correct
to say that the falling apart body and
mind of your last life
caused the falling apart body and mind
of this life
because the body and mind falling apart
in this life started.
And that one was ending. So, if they're
the same thing,
uh
they wouldn't have a cause and effect.
Okay? Could not have come from my death.
I cannot come from my death. Picture.
Okay.
Come again
uh
If your suffering body and mind came
from your past suffering body and mind,
then since your past body and mind were
already suffering, they didn't have to
create more suffering cuz they were
already suffering.
Nobody made them suffer.
They were suffer The cause was
suffering,
so the result was suffering, so no new
suffering was made.
Okay?
No new suffering was made.
If your nature is to suffer,
then no one has to make you suffer.
Okay?
If your nature is to suffer,
then you don't have to do anything.
You're going to suffer anyway. If your
nature is not to suffer,
and you try to make yourself self
suffer, you couldn't do it anyway.
Okay?
If your nature is not to suffer, then
nothing could make you suffer. If your
nature is to suffer,
then nobody would have to make you
suffer cuz you're already suffering.
Okay?
All right.
Uh
next verse.
Kelte
de le
Kelte de le de shin shin
Kelte te le de shin na de nya shin gi
che gyu shin
shin de da ki gech shin shin de da ki
gech gyu
Okay, this is how Chönyi Namkhai reads
this one.
Uh Kelte de le de shin shin
Uh if
if the body and mind falling apart that
you took in this life was coming from
body and mind
in your at your last death,
which is shin. Shin means
is the falling apart body and mind of
this life.
Is it your body and mind falling apart
in your last life? Yes or no? Is your
body and mind falling apart in this
life?
Your body and mind falling apart in your
last life.
Are they the same thing?
No.
No. They're the same experience, but but
one happens first and then the other one
happens, right?
Uh so, can we say that the falling apart
of your body and mind in this life
is different from the body from the
falling apart of your body and mind in
your past life? Are they different
things?
Yes.
Yeah, they're different things. Okay.
Kelte de le de shin na
If they were really different things,
de nya shin gi che gyu shin
shin de da ki gech gyu
Uh then you could say
the
if they were different, maybe you could
say
that the falling apart of your body and
mind in your last life
has caused the falling apart of your
body and mind in this life. That's okay.
If you had a body and mind falling apart
in your last life, so you did mean
things to other people to try to fix
your falling apart body and mind,
then you get a new falling apart body
and mind. Are those the same body and
mind or are they different body and
mind?
They're They're So, they're different,
right? They have to be, okay? Then they
never touch.
They never make contact.
So, how can two things that never make
contact affect each other?
If you play a shoot of billiard ball in
and it hits another billiard ball, there
has to be a point of contact, right? And
the the motion of the first ball creates
the motion of the second ball. If your
past life's suffering body and mind
impelled your present life's suffering
body and mind, then they should have
made contact at some point. But, if
things exist the way you think they do
outside of your seeds, they can never
make contact.
They cannot We already went through
that.
It's like your foot on the Where's the
middle part of your foot? Where Where
does the past meet the present?
Where does the past meet the future?
Okay? Can There cannot be contact
between two things if they are
self-existently
separate, okay? If they exist by
themselves from their own side,
they cannot make contact cuz they would
have to overlap, and they can't.
Okay?
If they did overlap, then your past life
would be your
your present life
for a little time.
Okay? They can't touch. There's nowhere
where they can touch.
Okay? There's no place where they can
touch. If If your past life touch your
present life, then the place where they
touch would be both your present life
and your past life, and that's not
possible. They have to be separate. If
they're completely separate like that,
then by the time your past life messed
up body and mind
Sorry, if it's still there, you haven't
died yet.
Okay, and you can't have a future body
and mind yet. If you have a future body
and mind, then your past body and mind
already died.
A thing which is already gone cannot
have a relationship with something
that's here. Not possible, okay?
Something that came the moment before
can never cause something which is here
now because there's no time for them to
touch.
Either the past thing would have to be
have his toe in the present
or the present thing would have to have
the edge of his bottom in the past.
Somebody would have to cross the line
for them to touch, okay? Got it?
Okay, and it's not possible it's not
possible. Don't blame something else for
causing your current suffering.
It can't be.
If it's gone, it can't do anything.
If it's not gone, you're still in your
past life.
All right.
All right, uh
I I have a picture here of a
finger and a cactus, all right.
Mhm.
This is different from the other finger
and cactus picture. Why? Guess what?
There's a space between the finger and
the cactus, okay? If
If things
never touch each other
you can't get hurt.
If your finger never touches the cactus,
you can't get hurt, okay? And the fact
is
that you can't your finger
your present suffering cannot touch your
past life suffering. Not possible. Okay,
cannot.
Okay?
Rebecca, if they never touch, can one
hurt the other?
No, if they never touch, then one cannot
cause the other. Now,
if you like and insist,
yeah, my current life suffering happens,
forget, I don't care about and my past
life suffering caused it. Did they
touch? No.
Can a cactus hurt your finger without
touching if your present life can have
trouble caused by your past life without
touching?
Yeah.
They can.
Okay, so you should run around like this
all day. Ow, ow, ow. Why? Cuz there's
cactus near Phoenix.
And it doesn't have to touch you to hurt
you.
Okay, it's not does have to touch me to
hurt you. Okay, then your past life has
to touch your present life.
Yeah, well what's wrong with that? They
have to overlap. Then part of your past
life has to be in the present to touch
your present life. Or part of your
present life has to be in the past to
get touched by your past life. But
that's not possible because your present
life is different from your past life.
If your present life had to touch your
past life, then you would be in your
past life.
Okay, got it?
It's not possible what you think is
happening.
It's not even possible what the Buddha
kept saying that what you did in your
past life is causing you suffering in
this life. That's not possible.
The Buddha
Something's wrong.
A cactus
that you never could touch is making
your finger hurt.
That's the same thing. Okay? I'll say it
again.
Don't look so confused. Or look
confused, that's okay.
If what you did in your past life is
causing you suffering in the present
life, then the past life has to touch
the present life in the same way that
your finger has to touch a cactus.
And if your finger can hurt without
touching the cactus, and if your present
life can have trouble without touching
your past life,
then
because there's cactuses in Arizona,
every time you cross the state line,
your finger should start hurting. Why?
Cuz they without touching, they can hurt
you.
I didn't What do you mean What's that
got to do with it? Because without your
past life touching your present life,
the events of your past life can hurt
your present life, according to you,
Buddha.
Got it? But they can't touch.
If they touch, then the very beginning
of your present life would have to be in
your past life, or the very end of your
past life would have to be in your
present life. And then there wouldn't be
a difference between past life and
present life.
Okay? It doesn't make sense. Yeshe, why
are you talking about this stuff? Who
cares? Who cares because you can't stop
suffering unless you figure out what's
where it's coming from. And it's not
coming from your past life, cuz your
past life can't touch your present life.
Well, where's it coming from? Oh, yeah,
we'll get there.
Okay.
All right, next verse.
Uh Kel te kham sa ta ki ni
uh ding ngak che na kham da ki ding ngak
che pe kham sa de ding ngak ma tok kham
shi yin, okay?
Uh if some kind of Now it's a person or
let's say
yeah, if someone else could hurt me,
uh then ding ngak che na kham da ki ding
ngak che pe kham sa de
then that person who caused me pain ding
ngak kham ma tok kham shi yin must cause
me pain all the time, okay? Or they
would be pain itself. If another person
can pain me,
then they are pain.
If another person can pain me, then they
are pain.
Okay? Got it?
If another person can
And we're always blaming our problems on
other people, right? All the time. All
every moment of the day.
But if a person could make you feel
pain, then they would have to be pain.
Cuz you're feeling pain
when you touch them.
Okay? Got it?
Okay.
And then then you can go a different
way, you know? I think you could take
this a different way. And Chönyi Lama,
you know, if you read Chönyi Lama, you
can take it this way. You can look at
the picture here. Okay?
Uh
I don't know. This is a guy
in an office. Uh
I don't know if this ever happened to
you in a job
that your boss is yelling at you. I
don't know.
It's almost the definition of a job.
Okay? So the boss is yelling at the guy.
Now, who's hurting whom?
Wait. Stay there. Yeah, good. Who's
hurting whom?
The boss is hurting the employee, right?
The employee looks sad.
The boss looks happy
cuz he gets to be the boss and he's
hurting the person.
Okay? So you can say the boss
hurt the
employee, right? Did the employee hurt
themselves?
Is the boss himself Is the boss the
employee?
That's the question here. I mean, that's
one of the big questions of this
chapter. Okay?
When someone else causes you suffering,
when your boss is yelling at you, who's
Who's yelling at you?
Who caused it?
Yes, so you're hurting yourself. Okay?
All right? You're hurting yourself.
Which we just said is impossible.
Okay.
Pain cannot hurt pain.
Right?
Okay, think about it. By the way, this
whole thing gets into blame.
You know, can you blame other people for
the trouble you have, right?
Or what caused cancer?
Okay, if the mantra's going to work to
stop the cancer,
then it's going to have to stop whatever
caused the cancer. So, then you got to
look at what really caused the cancer.
Cuz if it's the mantra's job to stop the
cancer, the mantra's going to have to
stop what caused the cancer. Because if
the mantra can't stop what caused the
cancer, then the more cancer's going to
come, okay? So,
does the mantra ever work
to stop cancer?
Then it would have to stop the cause of
the cancer, right?
And you have to think about that.
How can the mantra touch the cause of
the cancer when the cause of the cancer
is already gone?
How can you ever cure cancer with a
mantra?
Okay?
You would have to stop the cause of the
cancer, which is already gone already,
anyway. You don't need the mantra to
stop the cause of the cancer cuz the
cause of the cancer is already gone by
the time the cancer's there.
So, how are you going to stop the cancer
if you can't stop the cause of the
cancer?
How can you make contact with a thing
which is already in the past?
That's like writing your great grandma a
letter or something.
You know, okay?
Therefore, the way a mantra works to
stop your cancer is not what you think,
okay?
That you have to collect other seeds.
And again,
saving life is great. Saving some fish's
life is good.
And I think it gets you out of your
house and it gets you actually saving a
living being who's in front of you. And
And and there's nothing
as powerful as that.
But I think there are also lifestyle
choices you can make,
you know, about using your car or
or using plastic or things like that,
cutting down trees.
That would save a lot more lives. Okay.
Maybe you can do both.
All right.
Okay.
All right, next verse. He puts together
five, six
and seven. Here we go.
Uh
Uh if the pain I have is caused Kael Te
Kael Sa Shin Le Ni if another person can
cause me pain Deng Ya Che Na Shin Shi Ki
Deng Ya De Che Kael Jin De
then this
the suffering they caused me should
never stop. Why?
Because if if if the pain if the trouble
in my life is really caused by another
person,
then the word another
means a person who is not myself. Right.
Right. So, a person who is not myself
caused me some trouble in my life.
Right. That means they must have touched
you.
Right.
If they don't if they never make contact
with you in any way, then they can't
cause you trouble, right? Right. So,
they must have their life must have made
contact with your life in some way,
right? Right. So, they must overlap at
some point, right? No, they just touched
me. They don't overlap. Okay, so how did
they touch you without overlapping?
Well, just the edge of them of them
touches the edge of my trouble.
You know, come on, then there has to be
contact. There has to be some overlap.
Okay, so there is overlap, Geshe La.
Okay, then the other person and
and your trouble
are partly the same thing.
And anytime the person there to give you
trouble, I guess there are people like
that.
Okay, according to you, someone else is
causing the trouble problems in your
life. Yes, it's my partner. I don't have
trouble, they give me trouble. Okay, so
somebody else gives you trouble, right?
Right.
So they have to make contact with you on
some level, right?
They have to make contact with you to
give you trouble, right?
Yeah. So you in some way they become in
some point
they become you. The past
touches the present. So the last part of
the past is the first part of the
present cuz the last part of the past
has to start your trouble, right?
By the way, if the other person and your
trouble starting
were 1 millisecond apart, then they
couldn't make contact.
There's no point at which they make
contact, okay? The cause is gone, the
result is starting.
Well, that doesn't make sense cuz the if
the cause
causes the result, then the cause has to
share some milliseconds with the result.
Or else the or else something which is
not there is causing something which is
there, and that's not possible. That's
like a billiard ball
that already fell in the pocket is
making another ball move. You see what I
mean? It has to be there. They have to
both be on the table, okay?
So the person who causes you trouble
in your life
has to be
in the same moment and in the same place
as you
to do that. Yeah, so that means they're
not a cause, right? Why not? Cuz they're
past already.
By the time the tree grows from a seed,
the seed gone. By the time your partner
gives you trouble, and you got the
trouble, your partner has to be
invisible.
Not there. An invisible, non-existent
partner,
like a seed that disappeared after the
tree grew, is causing you trouble,
right?
Okay.
Uh so, the other guy is uh
This now Johnny Lama goes off on a bit
of a tangent, okay? And I'll go on I'll
go with him, okay?
He says, "When I say your current pain
is caused by somebody else,
I just mean
the actions taken by
a life form in the past, say an animal,
are causing the pain of a human in this
life. So, I'm not talking about the same
person.
That was an animal. This was a human.
I'm talking about different life forms."
He says, "That's That's possible."
Okay, they're not me.
The animal is a different life form.
Somebody other than me.
When I say somebody other than me has
caused me the trouble in this life, I'm
saying this human life's trouble was
caused by someone who was an animal or
That's what the other guy is trying to
say.
Then Then you should have suffering all
the time.
Okay, if they if they if someone can
cause you suffering,
if someone can give you trouble without
making contact with you,
then you should have trouble all the
time. Why? Cuz they're always not making
contact with you.
Then your whole life should be trouble
all the time. I'll say it again. If
someone can give you trouble without
making contact with you, then even when
they're not around, you should have
trouble.
Why? Cuz they don't have to make contact
with you to give you trouble, okay?
All right.
Then I chose a picture here. Um
Uh
Do you ever give pain to your future
self?
There you go. There's the answer.
Yeah.
Yeah. I don't know. Yesterday I made a
sweet rolls.
Someone was teaching me to make cinnamon
rolls for our cafe and uh
then I don't know why we all felt There
were four of us there and we all felt
that
because we were making them for a noble
purpose, we could eat them as much as we
wanted.
And we all ate like three or four of
them.
And uh
then afterwards, I was like, "What the
heck did I just do?"
You know? And uh
Yeah, I am causing pain for my future
self, but how is that if I never touched
them? If I'm gone, if the person who ate
the three or four cinnamon rolls is gone
by the time the other person gets fat,
then can you really say that someone
who's not there is giving someone
trouble to someone who is there?
Okay? It's not possible. It's actually
not possible.
Well, guess what? What's really going
on?
Some kind of karmic state is creating
the
eating the cinnamon roll,
and then another karmic state is
creating the fat person. But the
cinnamon roll doesn't cause the fat
person. In theory,
you should be able to eat cinnamon rolls
without getting fat.
Okay? We're still looking for the sweet
spot.
All right.
Let's go on to the next verse. And I
know it's hard. It's hard to have so
much in the garden in one day. It's
Hang in there.
Okay.
Are they actually doing a doctrine in
You can't say that pain causes pain
because the pain that causes the
present pain would have to be past pain
and that past pain would have to be
gone.
wrong
Okay. If I didn't cause my own pain then
something else caused my own pain but
also that thing was gone by the time I
had my own pain and something that was
gone was causing something that's not
gone.
Okay.
So the picture I have here
is I don't know why.
No one caused No one can cause me pain.
Okay. I cannot
Michael cannot cause Michael pain by
overeating.
Michael at 3:00 cannot cause trouble for
Michael at 4:00 by overeating at 3:00.
Why? Because Michael who overeats at
2:00 is gone by the time Michael at 4:00
is suffering. They never touched. They
never made contact. Okay.
So I cannot cause myself pain. Obviously
if someone else cooks me cinnamon rolls
and I eat too many of them, since they
never touched me, they didn't cause me
the pain either. Therefore, I didn't
have the pain. No, I had the pain.
It was coming from somewhere else.
All right, here we go.
Uh Kelty, next verse.
Then he skips over quickly the other two
possibilities. What?
Uh
say again.
Yeah, both and neither. Okay. Both
and somebody else causes Geshe-la to get
overweight.
Okay. Or nobody causes Geshe-la to get
overweight. Neither Geshe-la nor anyone
else causes Geshe-la to get overweight.
And he just dismisses those two.
Okay.
Uh
Picture?
Yeah.
It's a picture of two hands solving a
puzzle, I think.
Yeah.
Yeah, anyway, it's not both me and
someone else causing my pain.
And it's not nobody causing my pain.
Uh the nobody causing my pain is easy.
But
Geshe-la, how can you say that it's not
me and somebody else causing my pain?
Cuz they're gone by the time you have
the pain.
And something that's not there cannot
cause pain.
All right, here we keep going. Next
verse.
Uh
Um
He says, "Look,
we just finished the discussion of
suffering from four points of view.
Does suffering cause suffering? Does
something else cause suffering?
Does both itself and something else
cause suffering? Or does suffering
happen
a head to go
without any cause at all?" And he said,
"No."
He said no to all four. Okay.
Then he said, "Okay, take that principle
and apply it to everything else in your
life. Okay. Chiro Nupa Nam Layon.
Apply it to all the things around you in
your world. Okay. All the things around
you in your world are also not caused by
themselves, are not caused by something
else, are not caused by both, and are
not caused by nothing, but they are
caused. So, how does that happen? From
seeds in your mind. Okay.
You create
your mind creates the cause.
Your mind creates the result. Your mind
creates the connection between the cause
and the result, but the cause doesn't
cause the result. Okay? That's a
fallacy. That's wrong.
That means that everything everyone has
ever done on this planet who didn't
understand emptiness was mistaken. Every
action taken in the last few million
years
by any person in the world was mistaken
and didn't do what it was supposed to
do. It had no relationship to what they
wanted.
Every single action in human history was
worthless and useless.
All right.
And that is the joyful end of this third
class.
Every action taken by any living being,
animal or human,
in the history of this world, if they
didn't understand these things,
was useless and wrong.
Okay. See you guys in the next class.